<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>An answer to a letter written by the R.R. the Ld Bp of Rochester. Concerning the chapter of original sin, in the Vnum necessarium. / By Jer. Taylor D.D.</title>
            <author>Taylor, Jeremy, 1613-1667.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1656</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 99 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 59 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A95131</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing T286</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E1683_1</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R209161</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99868051</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99868051</idno>
            <idno type="VID">170258</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A95131)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 170258)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 210:E1683[1])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>An answer to a letter written by the R.R. the Ld Bp of Rochester. Concerning the chapter of original sin, in the Vnum necessarium. / By Jer. Taylor D.D.</title>
                  <author>Taylor, Jeremy, 1613-1667.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 111, [5] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by E. Cotes for R. Royston at the Angel in Ivie-lane,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London, :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1656.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>With two final advertisement leaves.</note>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "June 29.".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Warner, John, 1581-1666 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Church of England. --  Diocese of Rochester. --  Bishop (1637-1666 : Warner) --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Sin, Original --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-10</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-10</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-12</date>
            <label>Judith Siefring</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-12</date>
            <label>Judith Siefring</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:170258:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>An Anſwer to a Letter Written by the R. R. The L<hi rend="sup">d</hi> B<hi rend="sup">p</hi> of <hi>Rocheſter.</hi> Concerning The Chapter of <hi>Original Sin,</hi> In the <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>num Neceſſarium.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>By JER. TAYLOR D. D.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>London,</hi> Printed by <hi>E. Cotes</hi> for <hi>R. Royſton</hi> at the Angel in <hi>Ivie-lane,</hi> 1656.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="part">
            <pb facs="tcp:170258:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:170258:2"/>
            <head>An Anſwer to a Letter Written by the R. R. <hi>The L. B<hi rend="sup">p.</hi> of</hi> Rocheſter.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>R. R. Father and my good Lord,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>YOur Lordſhips Letter Dated <hi>July</hi> 28. I received not till <hi>Septemb.</hi> 11. It ſeems <hi>R. Roy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſton</hi> detained it in his hands, ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſing it could not come ſafely to me while I remain a priſoner. But I now have that liberty, that I can receive any Letters, and ſend any; for the Gentlemen under whoſe cuſtody I am, as they are carefull of their charges, ſo they are civil to my perſon. It was neceſſary I ſhould tell this to your Lordſhip, that I may not be under a ſuſpicion
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:170258:3"/>of neglecting to give accounts in thoſe particulars, which with ſomuch prudence and charity you were plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed to repreſent in your Letter con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning my diſcourſe of Original Sin. My Lord, in all your Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptions, I cannot but obſerve your candor and your paternal care con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning me. For when there was nothing in the Doctrine, but your greater reaſon did eaſily ſee the ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice and the truth of it, and I am perſwaded could have taught me to have ſaid many more material things in confirmation of what I have taught; yet ſo careful is your cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity of me, that you would not omit to repreſent to my conſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion what might be ſaid by captious and weaker perſons; or by the more wiſe and pious who are of a different judgement.</p>
            <p>But my Lord, firſt you are pleaſed to note that this diſcourſe runs not
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:170258:3"/>the ordinary channel. True; for if it did, it muſt nurſe the popular error: but when the diſeaſe is epidemical, as it is ſo much the worſe, ſo the extraordinary remedy muſt be ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledg'd to be the better. And if there be in it ſome things hard to be underſtood, as it was the fate of S. <hi>Paul</hi>'s Epiſtles (as your Lord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip notes out of S. <hi>Peter</hi>) yet this difficulty of underſtanding proceeds not from the thing it ſelf, nor from the manner of handling it, but from the indiſpoſition and prepoſſeſſion of mens minds to the contrary, who are angry when they are told that they have been deceived: for it is uſuall with men to be more diſpleaſed, when they are told they were in error, then to be pleaſed with them who offer to lead them out of it.</p>
            <p>But your Lordſhip doth with great advantages repreſent an ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jection
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:170258:4"/>of ſome captious perſons, which relates not to the material part of the Queſtion, but to the rules of art. If there be no ſuch thing as Original Sin tranſmitted from <hi>Adam</hi> to his poſterity, then all that ſixth chapter is a ſtrife about a ſhadow, a <hi>Non ens.</hi> A. It is true my Lord, the Queſtion as it is uſually handled, is ſo. For when the Franciſcan and Dominican do eternally diſpute about the conception of the Bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed Virgin, whether it was with, or without Original Sin, meaning by way of grace and ſpecial exemption, this is <hi>de non ente;</hi> for there was no need of any ſuch exemption: and they ſuppoſing that commonly it was otherwiſe, troubled themſelves about the exception of a Rule, which in that ſenſe which the ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pos'd it, was not true at all: ſhe was born as innocent from any im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>purity or formal guilt as <hi>Adam</hi> was
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:170258:4"/>created, and ſo was her Mother, and ſo was all her family. * When the Lutheran and the Roman diſpute, whether juſtice and original righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſs in <hi>Adam</hi> was Natural or by Grace, it is <hi>de non ente:</hi> for it was poſitively neither, but nega<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tively only; he had original righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs till he ſin'd, that is, he was righteous. till he became unrighte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous. * When the Calviniſt troubles himſelf and his Pariſhioners with fierce declamations againſt natural inclinations or concupiſcence, and diſputes whether it remains in bapti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zed perſons, or whether it be taken off by Election, or by the Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, whether to all Chriſtians or to ſome few; this is a <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>; for it is no ſin at all in perſons baptiz'd or unbaptiz'd, till it be conſented to.</p>
            <p>My Lord, when I was a young man in <hi>Cambridge,</hi> I knew a lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned profeſſor of Divinity, whoſe
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:170258:5"/>ordinary Lectures in the Lady <hi>Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>garets</hi> Chair for many years toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, nine as I ſuppoſe, or therea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bouts, were concerning Original Sin, and the appendant queſtions: This indeed could not chooſe but be <hi>Andabatarum conflictus.</hi> But then my diſcourſe repreſenting that theſe diſputes are uſeleſſe, and as they diſcourſe uſually to be <hi>de non ente,</hi> is not to be reprov'd. For I profeſſe to evince that many of thoſe things, of the ſenſe of which they diſpute, are not true at all in any ſenſe, I declare them to be <hi>de non ente,</hi> that is, I untie their intricate knots by cutting them in pieces. For when a falſe propoſition is the ground of diſputes, the proceſs muſt needs be infinite, unleſs you diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver the firſt error. He that tels them they both fight about a ſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dow, and with many arguments proves the vanity of their whole
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:170258:5"/>proceſſe, they (if he ſaies true) not he is the <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. * When S. <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtine</hi> was horribly puzled about the traduction of Original Sin, and thought himſelf forc'd to ſay that either the Father begat the ſoul, or that he could not tranſmit ſin which is ſubjected in the ſoul, or at leaſt he could not tell how it was tranſmitted: he had no way to be relieved but by being told that Ori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginal Sin was not ſubjected in the ſoul, becauſe properly and for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mally it was no reall ſin of ours at all; but that it was only by imputa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and to certain purpoſes, not any inherent quality, or corrupti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on: and ſo in effect all his trouble was <hi>de non ente.</hi> * But now ſome wits have lately riſen in the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> and they tell us another ſtory. The ſoul followes the tempe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rature of the body, and ſo Origi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal Sin comes to be tranſmitted by
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:170258:6"/>contact: becauſe the conſtitution of the body is the <hi>fomes</hi> or neſt of the ſin, and the ſouls concupiſcence is deriv'd from the bodies luſt. But beſides that this fancy diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>appears at the firſt handling, and there would be ſo many Origi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal Sins as there are ſeveral con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitutions, and the guilt would not be equal, and they who are born Eunuchs ſhould be leſſe infected by <hi>Adam</hi>'s pollution, by having leſſe of concupiſcence in the great in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance of deſires, [and after all, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cupiſcence it ſelf could not be a ſin in the ſoul, till the body was grown up to ſtrength enough to infect it] Beſides all this, (I ſay) while one does not know how Original Sin can be derived, and another who thinks he can, names a wrong way, and both the waies infer it to be another kinde of thing then all the Schools of learning teach [and in
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:170258:6"/>the whole proceſs it muſt be an im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſſible thing, becauſe the inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment which hath all its operations by the force of the principal agent, cannot of it ſelf produce a great change and violent effect upon the principal agent] does it not too clearly demonſtrate, that all that in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finite variety of fancies agreeing in nothing but in an endleſs uncertain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, is nothing elſe but a being buſie about the quiddities of a dream, and the conſtituent parts of a ſhadow? But then, My Lord, my diſcourſe repreſenting all this to be vanity and uncertainty, ought not to be call'd or ſuppos'd to be a <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>: as he that ends the queſtion between two Schoolmen diſputing about the place of Purgatory, by ſaying they need not trouble themſelves about the place; for that which is not, hath no place at all; ought not to be told he contends about a ſhadow, when he
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:170258:7"/>proves that to be true, which he ſug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geſted to the two trifling litigants.</p>
            <p>But as to the thing it ſelf: I do not ſay there is no ſuch thing as Original Sin, but it is not that which it is ſuppoſed to be: it is not our ſin formally, but by imputation on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly; and it is imputed ſo, as to be an inlet to ſickneſs, death and diſorder: but it does not introduce a neceſſity of ſinning, nor damn any one to the flames of Hell. So that Original Sin is not a <hi>Non ens,</hi> unleſs that be nothing which infers ſo many real miſchiefs.</p>
            <p>The next thing your Lordſhip is pleas'd to note to me, is that in your wiſdome you foreſee, ſome will argue againſt my explication of the word <hi>Damnation,</hi> in the ninth Article of our Church, which af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firms that Original Sin deſerves damnation. Concerning which, My Lord, I do thus (and I hope fairly) acquit my ſelf.</p>
            <pb n="11" facs="tcp:170258:7"/>
            <p n="1">1. That it having been affirmed by S. <hi>Auſtin</hi> that Infants dying un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baptized are damn'd, he is deſerved<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly called <hi>Durus pater Infantum,</hi> and generally forſaken by all ſober men of the later ages: and it will be an intolerable thing to think the Church of <hi>England</hi> guilty of that which all her wiſer ſons, and all the Chriſtian Churches generally ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>horre. I remember that I have heard that King <hi>James</hi> reproving a Scottiſh Miniſter, who refus'd to give private Baptiſm to a dying In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fant, being askt by the Miniſter, if he thought the childe ſhould be damn'd for want of Baptiſm? an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer'd, No, but I think you may be damn'd for refuſing it: and he ſaid well. But then my Lord, If Original Sin deſerves damnation, then may Infants be damn'd if they die without Baptiſm. But if it be a horrible affirmative, to ſay that
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:170258:8"/>the poor babes ſhall be made De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vils, or enter into their portion, if they want that ceremony, which is the only gate, the only way of ſalva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion that ſtands open; then the word <hi>[Damnation]</hi> in the 9. Article muſt mean ſomething leſs, then what we uſually underſtand by it: or elſe the Article muſt be ſalved by ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pounding ſome other word to an allay and leſſening of the horrible ſentence; and particularly the word <hi>[Deſerves]</hi> of which I ſhall after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards give account. Both theſe waies I follow. The firſt is the way of the Schoolmen.</p>
            <p>For they ſuppoſe the ſtate of un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baptized Infants to be a <hi>poena damni;</hi> and they are confident enough to ſay that this may be well ſuppos'd without inferring their ſuffering the pains of hell. But this ſentence of theirs I admit and explicate with ſome little difference of expreſſion.
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:170258:8"/>For ſo far I admit this <hi>pain of loſs,</hi> or rather a deficiency from going to Heaven, to be the conſequence of <hi>Adam</hi>'s ſin, that by it we being left <hi>in meris Naturalibus,</hi> could never by theſe ſtrengths alone have gone to Heaven. Now whereas your Lord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip in behalf of thoſe whom you ſuppoſe may be captious, is pleas'd to argue. That as loſs of ſight or eyes infers a ſtate of darkneſs or blindneſs: ſo the loſſe of Heaven in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fers Hell; and if Infants go not to heaven in that ſtate, whither can they go but to hell? and that's Damnation in the greateſt ſenſe. I grant it, that if <hi>in the event of things</hi> they do not go to Heaven (as things are now ordered) it is but too likely that they go to Hell: but I adde, that as all darkneſs does not infer horror and diſtraction of minde, or fearful apparitions and phantaſms: ſo neither does all Hell,
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:170258:9"/>or ſtates in Hell infer all thoſe tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments which the Schoolmen ſigni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie by a <hi>poena ſenſus</hi> (for I ſpeak now in purſuance of their way). So that there is no neceſſity of a third place; but it concludes only that in the ſtate of ſeparation from Gods preſence there is a great va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riety of degrees and kinds of evil, and every one is not the extreme: and yet by the way, let me obſerve, that <hi>Gregory Nazianzen</hi> and <hi>Nice<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tas</hi> taught that there is a third place for Infants and Heathens: and <hi>Irenaeus</hi> affirm'd that the evils of Hell were not eternal to all, but to the Devils only and the greater criminals. But neither they nor we, nor any man elſe can tell whether Hell be a place or no. It is a ſtate of evil; but whether all the damned be in one or in twenty places, we can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not tell.</p>
            <p>But I have no need to make uſe
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:170258:9"/>of any of this. For when I affirm that Infants being by <hi>Adam</hi> reduc'd and left to their meer natural ſtate, fall ſhort of Heaven; I do not ſay they cannot go to Heaven at all, but they cannot go thither by their naturall powers, they cannot with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out a new grace and favour go to heaven. But then it cannot pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſently be inferred, that therefore they go to hell; but this ought to be infer'd, which indeed was the real conſequent of it; therefore it is neceſſary that Gods Grace ſhould ſupply this defect, if God intends Heaven to them at all; and becauſe Nature cannot, God ſent a Saviour by whom it was effected. But if it be asked, what if this grace had not come? and that it be ſaid, that with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out Gods grace they muſt have gone to Hell, becauſe without it they could not go to Heaven? I anſwer, That we know how it is, now that God in his goodneſs hath
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:170258:10"/>made proviſions for them: but if he had not made ſuch proviſions, what would have been we know not, any more then we know what would have followed, if <hi>Adam</hi> had not ſinned; where he ſhould have liv'd, and how long, and in what circumſtances the poſterity ſhould have been provided for in all their poſſible contingencies. But yet, this I know, that it followes not, that if without <hi>this Grace</hi> we could not have gone to Heaven, that therefore we muſt have gone to Hel. For although the firſt was ordinarily impoſſible, yet the ſecond was abſolutely unjuſt, and againſt Gods goodneſs, and therefore more impoſſible. But becauſe the firſt could not be done by nature, God was pleaſed to promiſe and to give his grace, that he might bring us to that ſtate whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther he had deſign'd. us, that is, to a ſupernatural felicity. If <hi>Adam</hi> had not fallen, yet Heaven had not been
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:170258:10"/>a natural conſequent of his obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, but a Gracious, it had been a gift ſtill: and of <hi>Adam</hi> though he had perſiſted in innocence, it is true to ſay, that without Gods Grace, that is, by the meer force of Nature, he could never have ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riv'd to a Supernatural ſtate, that is, to the joyes of Heaven; and yet it does not follow, that if he had re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>main'd in Innocence, he muſt have gone to Hell. Juſt ſo it is in In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fants, Hell was not made for man, but for Devils; and therefore it muſt be ſomething beſides meer Nature that can bear any man thi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther: meer Nature goes neither to Heaven nor Hell. So that when I ſay Infants naturally cannot go to Heaven, and that this is a puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of <hi>Adam</hi>'s ſin, he being for it puniſhed with a loſs of his gracious condition, and devolv'd to the ſtate of Nature, and we by him left
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:170258:11"/>ſo; my meaning is, that this Dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation which is of our Nature, is but negative, that is, as a conſequent of our Patriarchs ſin, our Nature is left imperfect and deficient in order to a ſupernatural end, which the Schoolmen call a <hi>poena damni,</hi> but improperly: they indeed think it may be a real event, and final con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition of perſons as well as things: but I affirm it was an evil effect of <hi>Adam</hi>'s ſin: but in the event of things it became to the perſons the way to a new grace, and hath no other event as to Heaven and Hell directly and immediately. In the ſame ſenſe and to the ſame purpoſe I underſtand the word Damnation in the 9. Article.</p>
            <p>But the word [Damnation] may very well, truly, and ſufficiently ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifie all the purpoſes of the Article, if it be taken only for the effect of that ſentence which was inflicted
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:170258:11"/>upon <hi>Adam,</hi> and deſcended on his poſterity, that is, for condemnation to Death, and the evils of mortali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty. So the word is uſed by S. <hi>Paul</hi> 1 Cor. 11.29. <hi>He that eateth and drinketh unworthily, eateth and drinketh</hi> Damnation <hi>to himſelf.</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> is the word, but that it did particularly ſignifie temporal death and evils, appears by the inſtances of probation in the next words, <hi>For, for this cauſe ſome are weak a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt you, ſome are ſick, and ſome are fallen aſleep.</hi> This alſo in the Article. Original Sin deſerves dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation, that is, it juſtly brought in the angry ſentence of God upon Man, it brought him to death, and deſerv'd it: it brought it upon us, and deſerv'd it too. I do not ſay that we by that ſin deſerv'd that death, neither can death be properly a puniſhment of us till we ſuperadde ſome evil of our own; yet <hi>Adam</hi>'s
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:170258:12"/>ſin deſerv'd it ſo, that it was juſtly left to fall upon us, we as a conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quent and puniſhment of his ſin be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing reduc'd to our natural portion. <hi>In odioſis quod minimum eſt ſequi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mur.</hi> The leſſer ſenſe of the word is certainly agreeable to truth and reaſon: and it were good we us'd the word in that ſenſe which may beſt warrant her doctrine, eſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally for that uſe of the word, having the precedent of Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture.</p>
            <p>I am confirm'd in this interpre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation by the 2. §. of the Article: <hi>viz.</hi> of the remanency of concu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſcence or Original Sin in the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>generate. All the ſinfulneſs of Ori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginal Sin is the luſt or concupi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcence, that is, the proneneſs to ſin. Now then I demand, whether Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cupiſcence before actual conſent be a ſin or no? and if it be a ſin, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther it deſerves damnation? That
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:170258:12"/>all ſin deſerves damnation, I am ſure our Church denies not. If therefore concupiſcence before con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent be a ſin, then this alſo deſerves damnation where ever it is: and if ſo, then a man may be damned for Original Sin even after Baptiſm. For even after Baptiſm, concupi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcence (or the ſinfulneſs of Origi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal Sin) remains in the regenerate: and that which is the ſame thing, the ſame vitiouſneſs, the ſame enmity to God after Baptiſm, is as damna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, it deſerves damnation as much as that did that went before. If it be replied, that Baptiſm takes off the guilt or formal part of it, but leaves the material part behinde, that is, though concupiſcence re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mains, yet it ſhall not bring damna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to the regenerate or Baptized. I anſwer, that though baptiſmal re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>generation puts a man into a ſtate of grace and favour, ſo that what
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:170258:13"/>went before ſhall not be imputed to him afterwards, that is, <hi>Adam</hi>'s ſin ſhall not bring damnation (in any ſenſe) yet it hinders not, but that what is ſinful afterwards ſhall be then imputed to him, that is, he may be damn'd for his own concupi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcence. He is quitted from it as it came from <hi>Adam;</hi> but by Baptiſm he is not quitted from it, as it is ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jected in himſelf, if (I ſay) concu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſcence before conſent be a ſin. If it be no ſin, then for it, Infants un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baptized cannot with juſtice be damn'd; it does not deſerve dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation: but if it be a ſin, then ſo long as it is there, ſo long it de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerves damnation; and Baptiſm did only quit the relation of it to <hi>Adam</hi> (for that was all that went before it) but not the danger of the man. * But becauſe the Article ſuppoſes that it does not damn the regenerate or baptized, and yet that it hath the na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:170258:13"/>of ſin, it follows evidently and undeniably, that both the phraſes are to be diminiſhed and underſtood in a favourable ſenſe. As the phraſe [the Nature of ſin] ſignifies; ſo does [Damnation] but [the Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of ſin] ſignifies ſomething that brings no guilt, becauſe it is af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firm'd to be in the Regenerate, therefore [Damnation] ſignifies ſomething that brings no Hell: but [to deſerve Damnation] muſt mean ſomething leſſe then ordinary, that is, that concupiſcence is a thing not morally good, not to be allowed of, not to be nurs'd, but mortifi'd, fought againſt, diſapprov'd, <hi>con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demn'd</hi> and diſallowed of men as it is of God.</p>
            <p>And truly My Lord, to ſay that for <hi>Adam</hi>'s ſin it is juſt in God to condemn Infants to the eternal flames of Hell: and to ſay, that concupiſcence or natural inclinati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:170258:14"/>before they paſs into any act, could bring eternal condemnation from Gods preſence into the eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall portion of Devils, are two ſuch horrid propoſitions, that if any Church in the world would expreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly affirm them, I for my part ſhould think it unlawful to communicate with her in the defence or profeſſion of either, and do think it would be the greateſt temptation in the world to make men not to love God, of whom men ſo eaſily ſpeak ſuch horrid things. I would ſuppoſe the Article to mean any thing rather then either of theſe. But yet one thing more I have to ſay.</p>
            <p>The Article is certainly to be expounded according to the analo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gy of faith, and the expreſs words of Scripture, if there be any that ſpeak expreſly in this matter. Now whereas the Article explicating Ori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginal Sin affirms it to be that fault
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:170258:14"/>or corruption of mans nature (<hi>vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tium Naturae,</hi> not <hi>peccatum</hi>) by which he is far gone from ori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginall righteouſneſs, and is in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clin'd to evil: becauſe this is not full enough, the Article adds by way of explanation <hi>[So that the fleſh luſteth againſt the ſpirit]</hi> that is, it really produces a ſtate of evil temptations: it luſteth, that is, actually and habitually; [it luſteth againſt the ſpirit, and therefore deſerves Gods wrath and damnation] So the Article: <hi>Therefore;</hi> for no other reaſon but becauſe the fleſh luſteth againſt the ſpirit; not becauſe it can luſt, or is <hi>apta nata</hi> to luſt, but becauſe it luſteth <hi>actually, therefore it de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerves damnation:</hi> and this is <hi>Ori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginal Sin:</hi> or as the Article ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſes it, <hi>it hath the nature of ſin;</hi> it is the <hi>fomes,</hi> or matter of ſin, and is in the original of man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kinde,
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:170258:15"/>and deriv'd from <hi>Adam</hi> as our body is, but it deſerves not damnation in the higheſt ſenſe of the word, till the concupiſcence be actual. Till then, the words of
[Wrath and Damnation] muſt be meant in the leſs and more ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie ſignification, according to the former explication: and muſt on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly relate to the perſonal ſin of <hi>Adam.</hi> To this ſenſe of the Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticle I heartily ſubſcribe. For beſides the reaſonableneſs of the thing, and the very manner of ſpeaking us'd in the Article; it is the very ſame way of ſpeaking, and exactly the ſame doctrine which we finde in S. <hi>James,</hi> (Jam. 1.14.) <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>: <hi>Concupi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcence,</hi> when it is impregnated, <hi>when it hath conceiv'd, then it brings forth ſin: and ſin when it is in</hi> production, and <hi>birth, brings forth death.</hi> But in Infants, concu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſcence
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:170258:15"/>is innocent and a virgin, it conceives not, and therefore is without ſin, and therefore with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out death or damnation. * Againſt theſe expoſitions I cannot imagine what can be really and materially objected.</p>
            <p>But my Lord, I perceive the main outcry is like to be upon the authority of the <hi>Harmony of Confeſsions.</hi> Concerning which I ſhall ſay this, that in this Article the Harmony makes as good mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſick as bels ringing backward; and they agree, eſpecially when they come to be explicated and untwiſted into their minute and explicite meanings, as much as <hi>Lutheran</hi> and <hi>Calviniſt,</hi> as <hi>Papiſt</hi> and <hi>Proteſtant,</hi> as <hi>Thomas</hi> and <hi>Scotus,</hi> as <hi>Remonſtrant</hi> and <hi>Dor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drechtan,</hi> that is, as much as <hi>pro</hi> and <hi>con,</hi> or but a very little more. I have not the book with me here
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:170258:16"/>in priſon, and this neighbour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hood cannot ſupply me, and I dare not truſt my memory to give a ſcheme of it: but your Lord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip knows that in nothing more do the reformed Churches diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>agree, then in this and its ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pendages; and you are pleaſed to hint ſomething of it, by ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing that ſome ſpeak more of this then the Church of <hi>England:</hi> and <hi>Andrew Rivet,</hi> though unwil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lingly, yet confeſſes, <hi>de Confeſsio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nibus noſtris &amp; earum ſyntagmate vel Harmonia, etiamſi in non nul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lis capitibus non planè conveniant, dicam tamen, melius in concordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>am redigi poſſe quàm in Eccleſia Romana concordantiam diſcordan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tium Canonum, quo titulo decretum Gratiani, quod Canoniſtis regulas praefigit, ſolet infigniri.</hi> And what he affirmes of the whole collecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, is moſt notorious in the Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticle
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:170258:16"/>of Original Sin. For my own part I am ready to ſubſcribe the firſt <hi>Helvetian</hi> confeſſion, but not the ſecond. So much difference there is in the confeſſions of the ſame Church.</p>
            <p>Now whereas your Lordſhip adds, that though they are falli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, yet when they bring evidence of holy Writ, their aſſertions are infallible, and not to be contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicted: I am bound to reply, that when they do ſo, whether they be infallible or no, I will beleeve them, becauſe then though they might, yet they are not deceived. But as evidence of holy Writ had been ſufficient without their au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority: ſo without ſuch evidence their authority is nothing. But then, My Lord, their citing and urging the words of S. <hi>Paul,</hi> Rom. 5.12. is ſo far from being an evident probation of their Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticle,
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:170258:17"/>that nothing is to me a ſurer argument of their fallibi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity, then the urging of that which evidently makes nothing for them, but much againſt them: As 1. Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firming expreſly that death was the event of <hi>Adam</hi>'s ſin; the whole event, for it names no other; temporal death; according to that ſaying of S. <hi>Paul,</hi> 1 Cor. 15. <hi>In Adam we all die.</hi> And 2. Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firming this proceſs of death to be <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, which is and ought to be taken to be the allay or condition of the condemnati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. It became a puniſhment to them only who did ſin; <hi>but upon them alſo inflicted for</hi> Adam<hi>'s ſake.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A like expreſſion to which is in the Pſalms, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 106.32, 33. <hi>They angred him alſo at the waters of ſtrife, ſo that he puniſhed</hi> Moſes <hi>for their ſakes.</hi> Here was plainly
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:170258:17"/>a traduction of evil from the Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to <hi>Moſes</hi> their relative: For their ſakes he was puniſhed, but yet <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>for as much as</hi> Moſes <hi>had ſin'd:</hi> for ſo it fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowes, <hi>becauſe they provoked his ſpirit, ſo that he ſpake unadviſed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly with his lips.</hi> So it is between <hi>Adam</hi> and us. He ſin'd and God was highly diſpleaſed. This diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleaſure went further then upon <hi>Adam</hi>'s ſin: for though that on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly was threatned with death, yet the ſins of his children which were not ſo threatned, became ſo puniſhed, and they were by na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture heirs of wrath and damna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion; that is, for his ſake our ſins inherited his curſe. The curſe that was ſpecially and only threat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned to him, we when we ſin'd did inherit for his ſake. So that it is not ſo properly to be called, <hi>Ori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginal Sin,</hi> as <hi>an original curſe</hi> upon our ſin.</p>
            <pb n="32" facs="tcp:170258:18"/>
            <p>To this purpoſe we have alſo another example of God tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitting the curſe from one to ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther: Both were ſinners, but one was the original of the curſe or puniſhment. So ſaid the Prophet to the wife of <hi>Jeroboam,</hi> 1 King. 14.16. [<hi>He ſhall give Iſrael up be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe of the ſins of</hi> Jeroboam, <hi>who did ſin, and who made Iſrael to ſin</hi>] <hi>Jeroboam</hi> was the root of the ſin and of the curſe. Here it was alſo (that I may uſe the words of the Apoſtle) that <hi>by the ſin of one man</hi> [Jeroboam] <hi>ſin went out into all</hi> [Iſrael] <hi>and</hi> the curſe, captivity, or <hi>death by ſin, and ſo death went upon all men</hi> [of Iſrael] <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>in as much as all men</hi> [of Iſrael] <hi>have ſinned.</hi> If theſe men had not ſinned, they had not been puniſhed: I cannot ſay they had not been afflicted; for <hi>David</hi>'s childe was ſmit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:170258:18"/>for his fathers fault: but though they did ſin, yet unleſs their root and principal had ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, poſſibly they ſhould not have ſo been puniſh'd: For his ſake the puniſhment came. Upon the ſame account it may be, that we may inherit the damnation or curſe for <hi>Adam</hi>'s ſake, though we deſerve it; yet it being tranſmit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted from <hi>Adam</hi> and not particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larly threatned to the firſt poſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity, we were his heirs, the heirs of death, deriving from him an original curſe, but due alſo (if God ſo pleaſed) to our ſins. And this is the full ſenſe of the 12. verſe, and the effect of the phraſe <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>.</p>
            <p>But your Lordſhip is pleaſed to object that though <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> does once ſignifie
[For as much as] yet three times it ſignifies <hi>in</hi> or <hi>by.</hi> To this I would be content to
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:170258:19"/>ſubmit, if the obſervation could be verified, and be material when it were true. But beſides that it is ſo uſed in 2 Cor. 5.4. your Lordſhip may pleaſe to ſee it uſed (as not only my ſelf, but indeed moſt men, and particular<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly the Church of <hi>England</hi> does read it and expound it) in Mat. 26.50. And yet if <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> were written <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, which is the ſame with <hi>in</hi> or <hi>by,</hi> if it be rendred word for word, yet <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> twice in the Scripture ſignifies [for as much as] as you may read Rom. 8.3. &amp; Heb. 2.18. So that here are two places beſides this in queſtion, and two more <hi>ex abun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>danti</hi> to ſhew, that if it were not <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, but ſaid in words expreſly as you would have it in the mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, yet even ſo neither the thing, nor any part of the thing could be evicted againſt me:
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:170258:19"/>and laſtly, if it were not only ſaid <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> but that that ſenſe of it were admitted which is deſired, and that it did mean <hi>in</hi> or <hi>by</hi> in this very place: yet the Queſtion were not at all the nearer to be concluded againſt me. For I grant that it is true <hi>[in him we are all ſinners]</hi> as it is true that <hi>[in him we all die]</hi> that is, for his ſake we are us'd as ſinners; be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing miſerable really, but ſinners in account and effect: as I have largely diſcourſed in my book. But then for the place here in queſtion, it is ſo certain that it ſignifies the ſame thing (as our Church reads it) that it is not ſenſe without it, but a violent breach of the period without prece<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent or reaſon. And after all; I have looked upon thoſe places where <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> is ſaid to ſignifie <hi>in</hi> or <hi>by,</hi> and in one of them I finde it ſo,
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:170258:20"/>Mar. 2.4. but in Act. 3.16. &amp; Phil. 1.3. I finde it not at all in any ſenſe: but <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> indeed is uſed for <hi>in</hi> or <hi>by,</hi> in that of the Acts; and in the other it ſignifies, <hi>at</hi> or <hi>upon;</hi> but if all were granted that is pretended to, it no way prejudices my cauſe, as I have already pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved.</p>
            <p>Next to theſe your Lordſhip ſeems a little more zealous and decretory in the Queſtion upon the confidence of the 17, 18, &amp; 19. verſes of the 5. chapter to the Romans. The ſum of which as your Lordſhip moſt ingeniouſly ſums it up, is this.
<q>As by one many were made ſinners: ſo by one many were made righteous, that by <hi>Adam,</hi> this by <hi>Chriſt.</hi> But by Chriſt we are made <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> juſt, not by imputation only, but effectively and to real purpoſes; therefore by <hi>Adam</hi>
                  <pb n="37" facs="tcp:170258:20"/>we are really made ſinners. And this your Lordſhip confirms by the obſervation of the ſenſe of two words here uſed by the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle, The firſt is <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, which ſignifies a ſentence of guilt, or puniſhment for ſin, and this ſin to be theirs upon whom the condemnation comes, becauſe God puniſhes none but for their own ſin, Ezek. 18.2. From the word <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>clear from ſin,</hi> ſo your Lordſhip ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders it: and in oppoſition to this, <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> is to be rendred, that is, guilty, criminal per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, really and properly.</q> This is all which the wit of man can ſay from this place of S. <hi>Paul,</hi> and if I make it appear that this is invalid, I hope I am ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cure.</p>
            <p>To this then, I anſwer: That the Antitheſis in theſe words here
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:170258:21"/>urg'd, (for there is another in the chapter) and this whole argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of S. <hi>Paul</hi> is full and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tire without deſcending to mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nutes. Death came in by one man, much more ſhall life come by one man; if that by <hi>Adam,</hi> then much more this by Chriſt: by him to condemnation, by this man to juſtification. This is e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough to verifie the argument of S. <hi>Paul,</hi> though life and death did not come in the ſame manner to the ſeveral relatives; as indeed they did not: of which afterwards. But for the preſent: It runs thus. By <hi>Adam</hi> we were made ſinners; by Chriſt we are made righteous: As certainly one as the other, though not in the ſame man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of diſpenſation. By <hi>Adam</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> death reigned; by this man the reign of death ſhall be deſtroyed, and life ſet up in
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:170258:21"/>ſtead of it; by him we were us'd as ſinners, for in him we died: but by Chriſt we are juſtified, that is, us'd as juſt perſons, for by him we live. This is ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent for the Apoſtles argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and yet no neceſſity to af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firm that we are ſinners in <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam</hi> any more then by imputa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion: for we are by Chriſt made juſt no otherwiſe then by imputa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</p>
            <p>In the proof or perſwaſion I will uſe no indirect arguments, as to ſay, that to deny us to be juſt by imputation is the Doctrine of the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> and of the <hi>Socinian</hi> Conventicles, but ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſly diſlik'd by all the <hi>Luthe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ran, Calviniſt,</hi> and <hi>Zuinglian</hi> Churches, and particularly by the Church of <hi>England,</hi> and indeed by the whole Harmony of Confeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions:
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:170258:22"/>this I ſay, I will not make uſe of; not only becauſe I my ſelf do not love to be preſs'd by ſuch prejudices rather then arguments; but becauſe the queſtion of the imputation of righteouſneſs is very much miſtaken and miſun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtood on all hands. They that ſay that Chriſts righteouſneſs is imputed to us for juſtification, do it upon this account, becauſe they know all that we do is imperfect, therefore they think themſelves conſtrain'd to flie to Chriſt's righteouſneſs, and think it muſt be imputed to us, or we periſh. The other ſide, conſidering that this way would deſtroy the ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſity of holy living; and that in order to our juſtification, there were conditions requir'd on our parts, think it neceſſary to ſay that we are juſtified by inherent righteouſneſs. Between theſe the
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:170258:22"/>truth is plain enough to be read. Thus:</p>
            <p>Chriſt's righteouſneſs is not imputed to us for juſtification di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rectly and immediately; neither can we be juſtified by our own righteouſneſs: but our Faith and ſincere endevours are through Chriſt accepted in ſtead of legal righteouſneſs: that is; we are ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtified through Chriſt, by impu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation, not of Chriſts, nor our own righteouſneſs: but of our faith and endevours of righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs as if they were perfect: and we are juſtified by a Non-impu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation, <hi>viz.</hi> of our paſt ſins, and preſent unavoidable imperfecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons: that is, we are handled as if we were juſt perſons and no ſinners. So faith was imputed to <hi>Abraham</hi> for righteouſneſs; not that it made him ſo, <hi>legally,</hi> but <hi>Evangelically,</hi> that is, by grace and imputation.</p>
            <pb n="42" facs="tcp:170258:23"/>
            <p>And indeed My Lord, that I may ſpeak freely in this great queſtion: when one man hath ſin'd, his deſcendents and rela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tives, cannot poſſibly by him, or for him, or in him be made ſinners properly and really. For in ſin there are but two things imagina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble: the irregular action; and the guilt, or obligation to puniſhment. Now we cannot in any ſenſe be ſaid to have done the action which another did, and not we: the acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on is as individual as the perſon; and <hi>Titius</hi> may as well be <hi>Cajus,</hi> and the Son be his own Father, as he can be ſaid to have done the Fathers action; and therefore we cannot poſſibly be guilty of it: for guilt is an obligation to puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment for having done it: the acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and the guilt are relatives; one cannot be without the other: ſomething muſt be done inwardly
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:170258:23"/>or outwardly, or there can be no guilt. * But then for the evil of puniſhment, that may paſs further then the action. If it paſſes upon the innocent, it is not a puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment to them; but an evil in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flicted by right of Dominion; but yet by reaſon of the relation of the afflicted to him that ſin'd, to him it is a puniſhment. But if it paſſes upon others that are not in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nocent, then it is a puniſhment to both; to the firſt principally; to the Deſcendents or Relatives, for the others ſake; his ſin being im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puted ſo far.</p>
            <p>How far that is in the preſent caſe, and what it is, the Apoſtle expreſſes thus: It was <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>; verſ. 18. or <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, verſ. 16. a curſe unto condemna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, or a judgement unto con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demnation, that is, a curſe inhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rited from the principal; deſerv'd
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:170258:24"/>by him, and yet alſo actually de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcending upon us after we had ſin'd, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> or <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>; that is the judgement paſſed up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on <hi>Adam;</hi> the <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, or <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> was on him; but it prov'd to be a <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, or a through condemna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion when from him it paſſed upon all men that ſin'd. <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> and <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> ſometimes differ in degrees: ſo the words are uſed by S. <hi>Paul</hi> other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>where (1 Cor. 11.32.) <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>; a judgement to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vent a puniſhment, or a leſs to fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtal a greater in the ſame kinde: ſo here the <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> paſs'd further; the <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> was fulfilled in his poſterity paſſing on further, <hi>viz.</hi> that all who ſin'd ſhould paſs under the power of death as well as he: but this became formally and actual<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly a puniſhment to them only who did ſin perſonally: to them it was <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>.</p>
            <pb n="45" facs="tcp:170258:24"/>
            <p>This <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> or <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, is the <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, verſ. 17. the reign of death; this is called <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, verſ. 21. the reign of ſin in death: that is, the effect which <hi>Adam</hi>'s ſin had, was only to bring in the reign of death, which is already broken by Jeſus Chriſt, and at laſt ſhall be quite deſtroyed. But to ſay that ſin here is properly tranſmitted to us from <hi>Adam,</hi> formally, and ſo as to be inherent in us, is to ſay that we were made to do his action, which is a perfect contradiction.</p>
            <p>Now then your Lordſhip ſees that what you note of the mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> I admit, and is indeed true enough, and agree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able to the diſcourſe of the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle, and very much in juſtificati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of what I taught. <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifies a puniſhment for ſin, and this ſin to be theirs upon whom
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:170258:25"/>the condemnation comes. I ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſily ſubſcribe to it: but then take in the words of S. <hi>Paul,</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, by one ſin, or by the ſin of one the curſe paſſed upon all men unto condemnation; that is, the curſe deſcended from <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam;</hi> for his ſake it was propa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gated <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> to a real con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demnation, <hi>viz.</hi> when they ſhould ſin. For though this <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> or the curſe of death was threatned on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to <hi>Adam,</hi> yet upon Gods be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing angry with him, God reſol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved it ſhould deſcend: and if men did ſin as <hi>Adam,</hi> or if they did ſin at all, though leſs then <hi>Adam,</hi> yet the <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> or the curſe threatned to him ſhould paſs <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the ſame actual condemnation which fell upon him, that is, it ſhould actually bring them under the reign of death.</p>
            <pb n="47" facs="tcp:170258:25"/>
            <p>But then my Lord, I beſeech you let it be conſidered, if this <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> muſt ſuppoſe a puniſhment for ſin, for the ſin of him, his own ſin that is ſo condemn'd, as your Lordſhip proves perfectly out of Ezek. 18. how can it be juſt that the <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> condemna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion ſhould paſs upon us for <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam</hi>'s ſin, that is, not for his own ſin who is ſo condemn'd, but for the ſin of another? S. <hi>Paul</hi> eaſily reſolves the doubt, if there had been any. The <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, the reign of death paſſed upon all men <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> in as much as all men have ſinned. And now why ſhall we ſuppoſe that we muſt be guilty of what we did not, when without any ſuch <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> there is ſo much guilt of what we did really and perſonally? why ſhall it be that we die only for <hi>Adam</hi>'s ſin, and not rather as
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:170258:26"/>S. <hi>Paul</hi> expreſly affirms <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> in as much as all men have ſinned, ſince by your own argument it cannot be <hi>in as much as all men have not ſinned;</hi> this you ſay cannot be, and yet you will not confeſs this which can be, and which S. <hi>Paul</hi> affirms to have been indeed: as if it were not more juſt and reaſonable to ſay, that from <hi>Adam</hi> the curſe deſcended unto the condemnation of the ſins of the world, then to ſay the curſe deſcended without conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration of their ſins; but a ſin muſt be imagined to make it ſeem reaſonable and juſt to condemn us. [Now I ſubmit it to the judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of all the world, which way of arguing is moſt reaſonable and concluding: You my Lord in be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>half of others argue thus. <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> or condemnation cannot paſs up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on a man for any ſin but his
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:170258:26"/>own: Therefore every man is truly guilty of <hi>Adam</hi>'s ſin, and that becomes his own. Againſt this I oppoſe mine. <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> or condem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation cannot paſs upon a man for any ſin but his own: therefore it did not paſs upon man for <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam</hi>'s fin; becauſe <hi>Adam</hi>'s ſin, was <hi>Adam</hi>'s, not our own: But we all have ſinned, we have ſins of our own, therefore for theſe the curſe paſs'd from <hi>Adam</hi> to us. To back mine, beſides that common no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tices of ſenſe and reaſon defend it, I have the plain words of S. <hi>Paul; Death paſſed upon all men, for as much as all men have ſinned;</hi> all men, that is, the gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rality of mankinde, all that liv'd till they could ſin, the others that died before, died in their nature, not in their ſin, neither <hi>Adam</hi>'s nor their own, ſave only that <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam</hi> brought it in upon them, or
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:170258:27"/>rather left it to them, himſelf be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing diſrobed of all that which could hinder it.</p>
            <p>Now for the word <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, which your Lordſhip renders [clear from ſin] I am ſure no man is ſo juſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied in this world, as to be clear from ſin; and if we all be ſinners, and yet healed as juſt perſons, it is certain we are juſt by imputation only, that is, Chriſt imputing our faith, and ſincere, though not unerring obedience to us for righteouſneſs: And then the Antitheſis muſt hold thus; By Chriſt comes juſtification to life, as by <hi>Adam</hi> came the curſe or the ſin to the condemnation of death: But our juſtification which comes by Chriſt is by imputa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and acceptilation, by grace and favour: not that we are made really, that is, legally and perfectly righteous, but by im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>putation
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:170258:27"/>of faith and obedience to us, as if it were perfect: And therfore <hi>Adam</hi>'s ſin was but by im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>putation only to certain purpoſes; not real, or proper, not formal or inherent. For the grace by Chriſt is more then the ſin by <hi>Adam:</hi> if therefore that was not legal and proper, but Evangelical and gracious, favourable and imputa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive, much more is the ſin of <hi>Adam</hi> in us improperly, and by im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>putation. * And truly my Lord, I think that no ſound Divine of any of our Churches will ſay that we are <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> or <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> in any other ſenſe: not that Chriſts righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſs is imputed to us with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out any inherent graces in us, but that our imperfect ſervices, our true faith and ſincere endevours of obedience are imputed to us for righteouſneſs through Jeſus Chriſt: and ſince it is certainly
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:170258:28"/>ſo, I am ſure the Antitheſis be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween <hi>Chriſt</hi> and <hi>Adam</hi> can never be ſalved by making us ſinners really by <hi>Adam,</hi> and yet juſt or righteous by <hi>Chriſt</hi> only in ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptation and imputation. For then ſin ſhould abound more then grace; expreſly againſt the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour of our bleſſed Saviour, the glory of our redemption, and the words of S. <hi>Paul.</hi> But rather on the contrary is it true, That though by <hi>Chriſt</hi> we were really and legally made perfectly righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous, it follows not that we were made ſinners by <hi>Adam</hi> in the ſame manner and meaſure: for this ſimilitude of S. <hi>Paul</hi> ought not to extend to an equality in all things; but ſtill the advantage and prerogative, the abundance and the exceſs muſt be on the part of Grace: for <hi>if ſin does abound, grace does much more abound;</hi> and
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:170258:28"/>we do more partake of righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs by <hi>Chriſt,</hi> then of ſin by <hi>Adam. Chriſt</hi> and <hi>Adam</hi> are the ſeveral fountains of emanation, and are compar'd <hi>aequè,</hi> but not <hi>aequaliter.</hi> Therefore this argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment holds redundantly, ſince by Chriſt we are not made legally righteous, but by imputation only; much leſs are we made ſinners by <hi>Adam.</hi> This in my ſenſe is ſo in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finitely far from being an ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jection, that it perfectly demon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrates the main queſtion; and for my part I mean to relie up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on it.</p>
            <p>As for that which your Lord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip adds out of Rom. 5.19. That <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> ſignifies ſinners, not by imitation, as the <hi>Pelagians</hi> dream, but ſinners really and ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectively; I ſhall not need to make any other reply; but that 1. I do not approve of that gloſs of
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:170258:29"/>the <hi>Pelagians,</hi> that in <hi>Adam</hi> we are made ſinners by imitation; and much leſs of that which af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firms, we are made ſo properly and formally. But
[made ſinners] ſignifies, us'd like ſinners; ſo as [juſtified] ſignifies healed like juſt perſons: In which interpreta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion I follow S. <hi>Paul,</hi> not the <hi>Pelagians;</hi> they who are on the other ſide of the queſtion, follow neither. And unleſs men take in their opinion before they read; and reſolve not to underſtand S. <hi>Paul</hi> in this Epiſtle, I wonder why they ſhould fancy that all that he ſayes ſounds that way which they commonly dream of: But as men fancy, ſo the Bels will ring. But I know yovr Lordſhips grave and wiſer judgement, ſees not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly this that I have now opened, but much beyond it, and that you will be a zealous advocate
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:170258:29"/>for the truth of God, and for the honour of his juſtice, wiſdome and mercy.</p>
            <p>That which followes, makes me beleeve your Lordſhip reſolv'd to try me, by ſpeaking your own ſenſe in the line, and your tempta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion in the interline. For when your Lordſhip had ſaid that
<q>[My ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guments for the vindication of Gods goodneſs and juſtice are ſound and holy]</q> your hand run it over again and added [as ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtracted from the caſe of Original Sin.] But why ſhould this be ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtracted from all the whole Oeco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nomy of God, from all his other diſpenſations? Is it in all caſes of the world unjuſt for God, to im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pute our fathers fins to us unto eternal condemnation; and is it otherwiſe in this only? Certain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly a man would think this were the more favourable caſe; as be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:170258:30"/>a ſingle act, done but once, repented of after it was done, not conſented to by the parties inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſted, not ſtipulated by God that it ſhould be ſo, and being againſt all lawes and all the rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of the world: therefore it were but reaſon that if any where, here much rather Gods juſtice and goodneſs ſhould be relied up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on as the meaſure of the event. * And if in other caſes lawes be never given to Ideots and Infants and perſons uncapable, why ſhould they be given here? but if they were not capable of a Law, then neither could they be of Sin; for where there is no law, there is no tranſgreſſion. And is it un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>juſt to condemn one man to hell for all the ſin of a thouſand of his Anceſtors actually done by them? and ſhall it be accounted juſt to damn all the world for one ſin of
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:170258:30"/>one man? But if it be ſaid, that it is unjuſt to damn the innocent for the ſin of another; but the world is not innocent, but really guilty in <hi>Adam.</hi> Beſides that this is a begging of the queſtion, it is alſo againſt common ſenſe, to ſay that a man is not innocent of that which was done before he had a being; for if that be not ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent, then it is impoſſible for a man to be innocent. And if this way of anſwer be admitted, any man may be damned for the ſin of any Father; becauſe it may be ſaid here as well as there, that although the innocent muſt not periſh for anothers fault, yet the ſon is not innocent as being in his fathers loyns when the fault was committed, and the law cals him and makes him guilty. And if it were ſo indeed, this were ſo far from being an excuſe, to ſay
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:170258:31"/>that the Law makes him guilty, that this were abſolute tyranny, and the thing that were to be com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plain'd of.</p>
            <p>I hope, by this time your Lord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip perceives, that I have no rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon to fear that I praevaricate S. <hi>Paul</hi>'s rule: <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. I only endevour to un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand S. <hi>Paul</hi>'s words, and I read them <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, in proportion to, and ſo as they may not intrench upon the repu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation of Gods goodneſs and ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice: that's <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, to be wiſe unto ſobriety. But they that do ſo <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> as to reſolve it to be ſo whether God be honour'd in it, or diſho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour'd, and to anſwer all argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, whether they can or can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be anſwered, and to efform all their Theology to the ayre of that one great propoſition, and
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:170258:31"/>to find out waies for God to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed in, which he hath never told of, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> waies that are crooked and not to be inſiſted in, waies that are not right, if theſe men do not <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, then I hope I ſhall have leſs need to fear that I do, who do none of theſe things.</p>
            <p>And in proportion to my ſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity here, I am confident that I am unconcern'd in the conſequent threatning. If any man ſhall E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vangelize, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> any o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther doctrine then what ye have received, ſomething for Goſpel which is not Goſpel, ſomething that ye have not received, let him be accurſed. My Lord, if what I teach were not that which we have received, that God is juſt and righteous and true: that the ſoul that ſins the ſame ſhall die: that we ſhall have no cauſe
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:170258:32"/>to ſay, The Fathers have eaten ſowre grapes, and the childrens teeth are ſet on edge: that God is a gracious Father, pardoning iniquity, and therefore not exact<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing it where it is not: that Infants are from their Mothers wombs beloved of God their Father: that of ſuch is the Kingdome of God: that he pities thoſe ſouls who cannot diſcern the right hand from the left, as he declar'd in the caſe of the <hi>Ninevites:</hi> that to Infants there are ſpecial Angels appointed who alwaies behold the face of God: that Chriſt took them in his arms and bleſſed them, and therefore they are not hated by God, and accurſed heirs of Hell, and coheirs with Satan: that the Meſſias was promis'd be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore any children were born; as certainly as that <hi>Adam</hi> ſin'd be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore they were born: that if ſin
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:170258:32"/>abounds, grace does ſuperabound; and therefore children are with greater effect involv'd in the grace then they could be in the ſin: and the ſin muſt be gone before it could do them miſchief: if this were not the doctrine of both Teſtaments, and if the contrary were, then the threatning of S. <hi>Paul</hi> might well be held up againſt me: but elſe my Lord, to ſhew ſuch a Scorpion to him that ſpeaks the truth of God in ſincerity and humility, though it cannot make me to betray the truth and the honour of God, yet the very fear and affrightment which muſt needs ſeize upon every good man that does but behold it, or hear the words of that angry voice, ſhall and hath made me to pray not only that my ſelf be preſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved in truth, but that it would pleaſe God to bring into the way
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:170258:33"/>of truth all ſuch as have erred and are deceived.</p>
            <p>My Lord, I humbly thank your Lordſhip for your grave and pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Councel, and kiſſe the hand that reaches forth ſo paternal a rod. I ſee you are tender both of truth and me: and though I have not made this tedious reply to cauſe trouble to your Lordſhip, or to ſteal from you any part of your precious time, yet becauſe I ſee your Lordſhip was perſwa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded <hi>induere perſonam,</hi> to give ſome little countenance to a po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pular error out of jealouſie againſt a leſs uſual truth, I thought it my duty to repreſent to your Lordſhip ſuch things, by which as I can, ſo I ought to be defended againſt captious objectors. It is hard when men will not be pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent of truth, becauſe another man offers it to them, and they did
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:170258:33"/>not firſt take it in, or if they did, were not pleas'd to own it.</p>
            <p>But from your Lordſhip I ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pect, and am ſure to finde the ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fects of your piety, wiſdome and learning, and that an error for being popular ſhall not prevail againſt ſo neceſſary, though un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>obſerved truth. A neceſſary truth I call it; becauſe without this I do not underſtand how we can declare Gods righteouſneſs and juſtifie him, with whom unrighte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſſe cannot dwell: But if men of a contrary opinion, can reconcile their uſual doctrines of Original Sin with Gods juſtice, and goodneſs and truth, I ſhall be well pleaſed with it, and think better of their doctrine then now I can.</p>
            <p>But untill that be done, it were well (My Lord) if men would not trouble themſelves or
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:170258:34"/>the Church with impertinent con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tradictions; but patiently give leave to have truth advanced, and God juſtified in his ſayings and in his judgements, and the Church improved, and all errors confuted, that what did ſo proſperouſly be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gin the Reformation, may be ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted to bring it to perfection, that men may no longer go <hi>quâ itur,</hi> but <hi>quâ eundum eſt.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="part">
            <pb n="65" facs="tcp:170258:34"/>
            <head>
               <hi>The By of</hi> Rocheſter<hi>'s Letter to Dr.</hi> Taylor, <hi>with an account of the particulars there given in charge.</hi>
            </head>
            <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
               <body>
                  <opener>
                     <salute>WORTHY SIR,</salute>
                  </opener>
                  <p>—Let me requeſt you to weigh that of S. <hi>Paul,</hi> Epheſ. 2.5. which are ur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged by ſome Ancients: and to remember, how often he cals <hi>Concupiſcence Sin;</hi> whereby it is urg'd that although Baptiſm take a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:170258:35"/>the guilt as concre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tively redounding <hi>to the perſon,</hi> yet the ſimple ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtracted guilt, <hi>as to the Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture</hi> remains: for Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments are adminiſtred to <hi>Perſons,</hi> not to <hi>Natures.</hi> I confeſs, I finde not the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers ſo fully, and plainly ſpeaking of Original Sin, till <hi>Pelagius</hi> had pudled the ſtream: but, after this, you may finde S. <hi>Jerom</hi> in Hoſ. ſaying, <hi>In paradiſo omnes praevaricati ſunt in Adamo.</hi> And S. <hi>Ambroſe</hi> in Rom. 1.5. <hi>Manifeſtum eſt omnes peccaſſe in Adam, quaſi in maſſâ, ex eo igitur
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:170258:35"/>cuncti peccatores, quia ex eo ſumus omnes;</hi> and as <hi>Greg.</hi> 39 Hom. in Ezek. <hi>Sine culpâ in mundo eſſe non poteſt, qui in mundum cum culpâ ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nit;</hi> But S. <hi>Auſtin</hi> is ſo fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quent, ſo full and clear in his aſſertions, that his words &amp; reaſons will require your moſt judicious examinati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, and more ſtrict weigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of them; he ſaith epiſt. 107. <hi>Scimus ſecundùm A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam nos primâ nativitate contagium mortis contrahere; nec liberamur à ſupplicio mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tis aeternae niſi per gratiam renaſcamur in Chriſto; Id. de verb. Apoſt. Ser.</hi> 4. <hi>pec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>catum
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:170258:36"/>à primo homine in om<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes homines pertranſiit, etenim illud peccatum non in fonte manſit, ſed pertranſiit,</hi> and Rom. 5. <hi>ubi te invenit? ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nundatum ſub peccato, tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hentem peccatum primi ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minis, habentem peccatum antequam poſſis habere arbi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trium.</hi> Id. de praedeſtin. &amp; grat. c. 2. <hi>Si infans uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us diei non ſit ſine peccato, qui proprium habere non po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuit, conficitur, ut illud traxe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit alienum; de quo Apoſt. Per unum hominem peccatum intravit in mundum; quod qui negat, negat profectò nos eſſe mortales; quoniam mors eſt
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:170258:36"/>poena peccati. Sequitur, ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſe eſt, poena peccatum.</hi> Id. enchir. c. 9.29. <hi>Sola gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tia redemptos diſcernit à perditis, quos in unam per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditionis maſſam concreverat ab origine ducta communis contagio,</hi> Id. de peccator. mer. &amp; remiſſ. l. 1. c. 3. <hi>Concupi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcentia carnis peccatum eſt, quia ineſt illi inobedientia contra dominatum mentis, Quid poteſt, aut potuit naſci ex ſervo, niſi ſervus? ideo ſicut omnis homo ab Adamo eſt, ita &amp; omnis homo per Adamum ſervus eſt peccati.</hi> Rom. 5. <hi>Falluntur ergo om<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nino, qui dicunt mortem ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lam,
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:170258:37"/>non &amp; <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>peccatum tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiiſſe in genus humanum. Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſper. reſp. ad articulum Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guſtino falsò impoſitum; Om<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes homines praevaricationis reos, &amp; damnationi obnoxios naſci perituroſ<expan>
                           <am>
                              <g ref="char:abque"/>
                           </am>
                           <ex>que</ex>
                        </expan> niſi in Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſto renaſcamur, aſſerimus.</hi> Tho. 12. q. 8. <hi>Secundum fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dem Catholicam tenendum eſt, quod primum peccatum pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mi hominis, originaliter tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſit in poſteros, propter quod etiam pueri mox nati defe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>runtur ad baptiſmum ab in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teriore culpâ abluendi. Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trarium eſt haereſis Pelag. un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de peccatum quod ſic à pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mo parente derivatur, dici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:170258:37"/>Originale, ſicut pecca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum, quod ab animâ deriva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur ad membra corporis, dici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur actuale.</hi> Bonavent. in 2. ſent. diſt. 31. <hi>Sicut pec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>catum actuale tribuitur ali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cui ratione ſingularis perſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nae: ita peccatum originale tribuitur ratione Naturae; corpus infectum traducitur, quia perſona Adae infecit na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turam, &amp; natura infecit per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonam. Anima enim inficitur à carne per colligantiam, quum unita carni traxit ad ſe al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terius proprietates.</hi> Lombar. 2. Sent. diſt. 31. <hi>Peccatum originale per corruptionem car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nis, in animâ fit: in vaſe enim
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:170258:38"/>dignoſcitur vitium eſſe, quod vinum acceſcit.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>If you take into conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration the Covenant made between Almighty God and <hi>Adam</hi> as relating to his poſterity, it may conduce to the ſatisfaction of thoſe who urge it for a proof of Origial Sin. Now that the work may proſper under your hands to the manife<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtation of Gods glory, the edification of the Church, and the ſatisfaction of all good Chriſtians, is the hear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty prayer of</p>
                  <closer>
                     <signed>Your fellow Servant in our moſt Bleſſed Lord Chriſt Jeſu. <hi>Jo. Roffenſ.</hi>
                     </signed>
                  </closer>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
               <body>
                  <pb n="73" facs="tcp:170258:38"/>
                  <opener>
                     <salute>My Lord,</salute>
                  </opener>
                  <p>I Perceive that you have a great Charity to every one of the ſons of the Church, that your Lordſhip refuſes not to ſollicite their objections, and to take care that every man be anſwered that can make objections againſt my Doctrine; but as your charity makes you refuſe no work or la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour of love: ſo ſhall my duty and obedience make me ready to perform any commandement that can be relative to ſo excellent a principle.</p>
                  <p>I am indeed ſorry your Lord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip is thus haunted with obje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions about the Queſtion of Ori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginal
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:170258:39"/>Sin; but becauſe you are pleas'd to hand them to me, I cannot think them ſo inconſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable as in themſelves they ſeem; for what your Lordſhip thinks worthy the reporting from others, I muſt think are fit to be anſwe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red and returned by me.</p>
                  <p>In your Lordſhips of <hi>Novem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber,</hi> 10. theſe things I am to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply to:</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Let me requeſt you to weigh that of S.</hi> Paul <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 2.5. The words are theſe [<hi>Even when we were dead in ſins,</hi> (God) <hi>hath quickned us together with Chriſt</hi>] which words I do not at all ſuppoſe relate to the matter of <hi>Original Sin,</hi> but to the ſtate of <hi>Heathen ſins, habitual Idolatries</hi> and <hi>impurities;</hi> in which the world was dead before the great Reformation by Chriſt. And I do not know any Expo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitor of note that ſuſpects any
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:170258:39"/>other ſenſe of it; and the ſecond verſe of that chapter makes it ſo certain and plain, that it is too viſible to inſiſt upon it longer. But your Lordſhip addes fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>And to remember how often he cals concupiſcence Sin</hi>] I know S. <hi>Paul</hi> reckons <hi>Concupiſcence</hi> to be one of the works of the fleſh, and conſequently ſuch as excludes from heaven, Col. 3.5. <hi>Evil concupiſcence</hi>] concupiſcence with ſomething ſuperadded, but cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly that is nothing that is <hi>na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tural;</hi> for God made nothing that is evil, and whatſoever is <hi>natural</hi> and <hi>neceſſary</hi> cannot be mortified; but this may and muſt, and the Apoſtle cals upon us to do it; but that this is a ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>inducing, and an <hi>actual</hi> or <hi>habi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual luſting</hi> appears by the fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing words, verſ. 7. <hi>in which
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:170258:40"/>ye alſo walked ſometimes when ye lived in them,</hi> ſuch a concupi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcence as that which is the effect of habitual ſins or an eſtate of ſins, of which the Apoſtle ſpeaks, Rom. 7.8. <hi>Sin taking occaſion by the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandement wrought in me all man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of concupiſcence;</hi> that is, ſo great a ſtate of evil, ſuch ſtrong incli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nations and deſires to ſin, that I grew as captive under it; it in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>troduced a neceſſity like thoſe in S. <hi>Peter,</hi> who had eyes <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> full of an Adultereſs: the women had poſſeſſed their eyes, and therefore they were <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <hi>they could not ceaſe from ſin:</hi> becauſe having <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <hi>all concupiſcence,</hi> that is the very ſpirit of ſinful deſires, they could reliſh nothing but the producti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of ſin, they could fancy no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing but Colloquintida and Toad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtools of the earth. * Once more
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:170258:40"/>I finde S. <hi>Paul</hi> ſpeaking of Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cupiſcence, 1 Theſſ. 4.5. <hi>Let every man knew to poſſeſs his veſſel in holineſs and honour, not in the luſt of concupiſcence, as do the Gentiles which know not God.</hi> In the <hi>luſt of Concupiſcence,</hi> that is plainly in luſtfulneſs and im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>purity: for it is a Hebraiſm, where a ſuperlative is uſually ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſed by the <hi>ſynonymon:</hi> as <hi>Lutum coeni; pluvia imbris;</hi> ſo <hi>the Gall of bitterneſs</hi> and the <hi>ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quity of ſins; Robur virium; the blackneſs of darkneſs,</hi> that is, <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, <hi>the outer darkneſs,</hi> or the greateſt darkneſs: ſo here <hi>the luſt of Concupiſcence,</hi> that is, the vileſt and baſeſt of it. I know no where elſe that the Apoſtle uſes the word in any ſenſe. But the like is to be ſaid of the word <hi>luſt,</hi> which the Apoſtle often uſes, for the <hi>habits produced</hi> or <hi>the preg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:170258:41"/>deſires,</hi> but never for the na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tural principle and affection, when he ſpeaks of ſin.</p>
                  <p>But your Lordſhip is pleaſed to adde a ſubtlety in purſuance of your former advices and notices, which I confeſs I ſhall never un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Although Baptiſm take away the guilt as concretively redound<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the perſon, yet the ſimple abſtracted guilt as to the Nature remains; for Sacraments are ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miniſtred to perſons, not to na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures]</hi> Thus I ſuppoſe thoſe per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons from whom your Lord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip reports it, intended as an an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer to a ſecret objection. For if Concupiſcence be a ſin, and yet remains after baptiſm, then what good does Baptiſm effect? But if it be no ſin after, then it is no ſin before. To this it is anſwered as you ſee: there is a
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:170258:41"/>double guilt; <hi>a guilt of perſon,</hi> and <hi>of nature.</hi> That is taken away, <hi>this</hi> is not: for, Sacraments are given to Perſons, not to Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures.</p>
                  <p>But firſt, where is there ſuch a diſtinction ſet down in Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture, or in the prime antiquity, or in any moral Philoſopher? There is no humane nature but what is in the perſons of men; and though our underſtanding can make a ſeparate conſideration of theſe, or rather conſider a per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon in a double capacity, in his perſonal and in his natural, that is (if I am to ſpeak ſenſe) a perſon may be conſidered in that which is proper to him, and in that which is common to him and others; yet theſe two conſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions cannot make two diſtinct ſubjects capable of ſuch different events. I will put it to the trial.</p>
                  <pb n="80" facs="tcp:170258:42"/>
                  <p>This guilt that is in nature, what is it? Is it the ſame thing that was in the perſon? that is, is it an obligation to puniſhment? If it be not, I know not the meaning of the word, and therefore I have nothing to do with it. If it be, then if this guilt or obliga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to puniſhment remains in the nature after it is taken from the perſon, then if this concupiſcence deſerve damnation, this nature ſhall be damned, though the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon be ſaved. Let the Objectors, my Lord, chooſe which they will. If it does not deſerve damnation, why do they ſay it does? If it does, then the guilty may ſuffer what they deſerve, but the inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent or the abſolved muſt not; the perſon then being acquitted, and the nature not acquitted, the nature ſhall be damn'd and the perſon be ſaved.</p>
                  <pb n="81" facs="tcp:170258:42"/>
                  <p>But if it be ſaid that the guilt remains in the <hi>nature</hi> to certain purpoſes, but not to all; then I reply, ſo it does in the <hi>perſon;</hi> for it is in the <hi>perſon</hi> after Baptiſm, ſo as to be a perpetual poſſibili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty and proneneſs to ſin, and a principle of trouble; and if it be no otherwiſe in the nature, then this diſtinction is to no purpoſe; if it be otherwiſe in the nature, then it brings damnation to it, when it brings none to the Man, and then the former argument muſt return. But whether it pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vail or no, yet I cannot but note, that what is here affirmed is ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſly againſt the words common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly attributed to S. <hi>Cyprian (De ablutione pedum) Sic abluit quos parentalis labes infecerat, ut nec actualis nec Originalis macula poſt ablutionem illam ulla ſui veſtigia derelinquat:</hi> How this ſuppoſing
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:170258:43"/>it of Baptiſm can be reconcil'd with the guilt remaining in the nature, I confeſs I cannot give an account. It is expreſly againſt S. <hi>Auſtin (Tom.</hi> 9. <hi>Tract.</hi> 41. <hi>in Johan. epiſt. ad Ocean.</hi>) ſaying, <hi>deleta eſt tota iniquitas!</hi> expreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly againſt S. <hi>Hierom, Quomodo juſtificati ſumus &amp; ſanctificati, ſi peccatum aliquid in nobis relin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quitur?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>But again (My Lord) I did ſuppoſe that <hi>Concupiſcence</hi> or <hi>Ori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginal Sin</hi> had been founded in nature, and had not been a <hi>per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonal</hi> but a <hi>natural evil.</hi> I am ſure, ſo the Article of our Church affirms; <hi>it is the fault and cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruption of our Nature.</hi> And ſo S. <hi>Bonaventure</hi> affirms in the words cited by your Lordſhip in your Letter: <hi>Sicut peccatum actu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ale tribuitur alicui ratione ſingula<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ris perſonae: ita peccatum origi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uis
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:170258:43"/>tribuitur ratione naturae.</hi> Ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther then the Sacrament muſt have effect upon our Nature, to purifie that which is vitiated by Concupiſcence, or elſe it does no good at all. For if the guilt or ſin be founded in the nature, (as the Article affirms) and Baptiſm does not take off the guilt from the nature, then it does no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing.</p>
                  <p>Now ſince your Lordſhip is pleas'd in the behalf of the ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jectors ſo warily to avoid what they thought preſſing, I will take leave to uſe the advantages it miniſters: for ſo the Serpent teaches us where to ſtrike him, by his ſo warily and guiltily de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fending his head. I therefore argue thus.</p>
                  <p>Either Baptiſm does not take off the guilt of Original Sin, or elſe there may be puniſhment
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:170258:44"/>where there is no guilt, or elſe natural death was not it which God threatned as the puniſhment of <hi>Adam</hi>'s fact. For it is cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain, that all men die as well af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter baptiſm as before; and more after then before. That which would be properly the conſequent of this Dilemma, is this, that when God threatned death to <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam,</hi> ſaying, <hi>On the day thou ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt of the tree thou ſhalt die the death,</hi> he inflicted and intended to inflict the evils of a trouble<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome mortal life. For <hi>Adam</hi> did not die that day, but <hi>Adam</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gan to be miſerable that day, to live upon hard labour, to eat fruits from an accurſed field, till he ſhould return to the earth whence he was taken. (Gen. 3.17, 18, 19.) So that death in the common ſenſe of the word was to be the end of his labour,
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:170258:44"/>not ſo much the puniſhment of the ſin. For it is probable he ſhould have gone off from the ſcene of this world to a better, though he had not ſin'd; but if he had not ſin'd, he ſhould not be ſo afflicted, and he ſhould not have died <hi>daily</hi> till he had di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed <hi>finally,</hi> that is, till he had <hi>returned to his duſt whence he was taken,</hi> and whither he would naturally have gone: and it is no new thing in Scripture that mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeries and infelicities ſhould be cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led <hi>dying</hi> or <hi>death.</hi> (Exod. 10.17. 1 Cor. 15.31. 2 Cor. 1.10. &amp; 4.10, 11, 12. &amp; 11.23.) But I only note this as probable; as not being willing to admit what the <hi>Socinians</hi> anſwer in this argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment; who affirm that God threatning death to the Sin of <hi>Adam,</hi> meant <hi>death eternal:</hi> which is certainly not true; as we learn
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:170258:45"/>from the words of the Apoſtle, ſaying, <hi>In Adam we all die;</hi> which is not true of <hi>death eternal,</hi> but it is true of the miſeries and cala<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mities of mankinde, and it is true of temporal death in the ſenſe now explicated, and in that which is commonly received.</p>
                  <p>But I add alſo this probleme. That which would have been, had there been no ſin, and that which remains when the ſin or guiltineſs is gone, is not properly the puniſhment of the ſin. But diſſolution of the ſoul and body ſhould have been, if <hi>Adam</hi> had not ſin'd, for the world would have been too little to have en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tertain'd thoſe myriads of men which muſt in all reaſon have been born from that bleſſing of <hi>Increaſe and multiply,</hi> which was given at the firſt Creation; and to have confin'd mankinde to the
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:170258:45"/>pleaſures of this world, in caſe he had not fallen, would have been a puniſhment of his innocence; but however, it might have been, though God had not been angry, and ſhall ſtill be, even when the ſin is taken off. The proper con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequent of this will be, that when the Apoſtle ſayes, <hi>Death came in by ſin,</hi> and that <hi>Death is the wages of ſin,</hi> he primarily and literally means the ſolemnities, and cauſes, and infelicities, and untimelineſs of temporal death, and not meer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly the diſſolution, which is direct<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly no evil, but an inlet to a better ſtate. But I infiſt not on this, but offer it to the conſideration of inquiſitive and modeſt perſons.</p>
                  <p>And now that I may return thi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther from whence this objection brought me; I conſider, that if any ſhould urge this argument to me:</p>
                  <p>Baptiſm delivers from Origi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal Sin.</p>
                  <pb n="88" facs="tcp:170258:46"/>
                  <p>Baptiſm does not deliver from <hi>Concupiſcence;</hi> therefore <hi>Concu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſcence</hi> is not Original Sin.</p>
                  <p>I did not know well what to an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer; I could poſſibly ſay ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing to ſatisfie the boyes &amp; young men at a publique diſputation, but not to ſatisfie my ſelf when I am upon my knees and giving an ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count to God of all my ſecret and hearty perſwaſions. But I con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider, that by <hi>Concupiſcence</hi> muſt be meant either the firſt inclina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions to their object; or the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per acts of Election which are the ſecond acts of <hi>Concupiſcence.</hi> If the firſt inclinations be meant, then certainly that cannot be a ſin which is <hi>natural,</hi> and which is <hi>ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary.</hi> For I conſider that Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cupiſcence and natural deſires are like <hi>hunger;</hi> which while it is natural and neceſſary, is not for the deſtruction but conſervation
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:170258:46"/>of man; when it goes beyond the limits of nature, it is violent and a diſeaſe: and ſo is <hi>Concupiſcence;</hi> But deſires or luſtings when they are taken for the natural propen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſity to their proper object, are ſo far from being a ſin, that they are the inſtruments of felicity for this duration, and when they grow towards being irregular, they may, if we pleaſe, grow inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of felicity in order to the other duration, becauſe they may ſerve a vertue by being reſtrai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned; And <hi>to deſire</hi> that to which all men tend naturally, is no more a ſin then to deſire to be happy is a ſin: <hi>deſire</hi> is no more a ſin then <hi>joy</hi> or <hi>ſorrow</hi> is: nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther can it be fancied why one paſſion more then another can be in its whole nature Criminal; either all or none are ſo; when any of them growes irregular or
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:170258:47"/>inordinate, Joy is as bad as Deſire, and Fear as bad as either.</p>
                  <p>But if by <hi>Concupiſcence</hi> we mean the ſecond acts of it, that is, avoidable conſentings, and deliberate elections, then let it be as much condemned as the Apoſtle and all the Church after him hath ſentenc'd it; but then it is not <hi>Adam</hi>'s ſin, but our own by which we are condemned; for it is not his fault that we chooſe; If we chooſe, it is our own; if we chooſe not, it is no fault. For there is a natural act of the Will as well as of the Underſtanding, and in the choice of the ſupreme Good, and in the firſt apprehen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of its proper object, the Will is as natural as any other faculty; and the other faculties have de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grees of adherence as well as the Will: ſo have the poteſtative and intellective faculties; they are <hi>de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lighted</hi>
                     <pb n="91" facs="tcp:170258:47"/>in their beſt objects. But becauſe theſe only are natural, and the will is natural ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times, but not alwaies, there it is that a difference can be.</p>
                  <p>For I conſider, if the firſt Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cupiſcence be a ſin, Original Sin, (for actual it is not) and that this is <hi>properly, perſonally,</hi> and <hi>inhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rently</hi> our ſin by traduction, that is, if our will be neceſſitated to ſin by <hi>Adam</hi>'s fall, as it muſt needs be if it can ſin when it can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not deliberate, then there can be no reaſon told, why it is more a ſin to will evil, then to underſtand it: and how does that which is moral differ from that which is natural? for the underſtanding is firſt and primely moved by its object, and in that motion by no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing elſe but by God, who moves all things: and if that which hath nothing elſe to move it but the
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:170258:48"/>object, yet is not free; it is ſtrange that the will can in any ſenſe be free, when it is neceſſitated by <hi>wiſdome</hi> and by <hi>power,</hi> and by <hi>Adam,</hi> that is, <hi>from within</hi> and <hi>from without,</hi> beſides what <hi>God</hi> and <hi>violence</hi> do and can do.</p>
                  <p>But in this I have not only Scripture and all the reaſon of the world on my ſide, but the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plying ſentences of the moſt emi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent writers of the Primitive Church; I need not trouble my ſelf with citations of many of them, ſince <hi>Calvin</hi> (<hi>lib.</hi> 3. <hi>Inſtit. c.</hi> 3. § 10.) confeſſes that S. <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtin</hi> hath collected their teſtimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies and is of their opinion, that Concupiſcence is not a <hi>ſin,</hi> but an <hi>infirmity</hi> only. But I will here ſet down the words of S. <hi>Chry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoſtome</hi> (<hi>Homil.</hi> 13. <hi>in epiſt. Rom.</hi>) becauſe they are very clear; <hi>Ipſae paſsiones in ſe peccatum non ſunt
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:170258:48"/>Effraenata verò ipſarum immode<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rantia peccatum operata eſt. Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cupiſcentia quidem peccatum non eſt quando verò egreſſa modum fo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ras eruperit, tunc demum adulte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rium ſit, non à concupiſcentia ſed à nimio &amp; illicito illius luxu.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>By the way I cannot but wonder why men are pleaſed, where ever they finde the word <hi>Concupiſcence</hi> in the New Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtament, preſently to dream of <hi>Original Sin,</hi> and make that to be the ſum total of it; whereas <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cupiſcence</hi> if it were the product of <hi>Adam</hi>'s fall, is but one ſmall part of it; <hi>[Et ut exempli gratiae unam illarum tractem]</hi> ſaid S. <hi>Chry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoſtome</hi> in the forecited place; <hi>Concupiſcence</hi> is but one of the paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions, and in the utmoſt extenſion of the word, it can be taken but for one half of the paſſion; for not only all the paſſions of the
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:170258:49"/>Concupiſcible faculty can be a principle of ſin, but the Iraſcible does more hurt in the world; <hi>that</hi> is more <hi>ſenſual, this</hi> is more <hi>devilliſh.</hi> The reaſon why I note this, is becauſe upon this account it will ſeem, that <hi>concupiſcence</hi> is no more to be called a ſin then <hi>anger</hi> is, and as S. <hi>Paul</hi> ſaid, <hi>Be angry, but ſin not;</hi> ſo he might have ſaid, <hi>Deſire,</hi> or <hi>luſt, but ſin not.</hi> For there are ſome luſtings and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſires without ſin, as well as ſome Angers; and that which is indiffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent to vertue and vice, cannot of it ſelf be a vice; To which I add, that if <hi>Concupiſcence</hi> taken for all de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſires be a ſin, then ſo are all the paſſions of the Iraſcible faculty. Why one more then the other is not to be told, but that Anger in the firſt motions is not a ſin, ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pears, becauſe it is not alwaies ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful in the ſecond; a man may
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:170258:49"/>be actually angry, and yet really innocent: and ſo he may be <hi>luſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful</hi> and <hi>full of deſire,</hi> and yet he may be not only that which is good, or he may overcome his deſires to that which is bad. I have now conſidered what your Lordſhip received from others, and gave me in charge your ſelf, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning concupiſcence.</p>
                  <p>Your next charge is concerning <hi>Antiquity,</hi> intimating that al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though the firſt antiquity is not clearly againſt me, yet the ſecond is. For thus your Lordſhip is pleaſed to write their objection [<hi>I confeſs I finde not the Fathers ſo fully and plainly ſpeaking of Original Sin, till</hi> Pelagius <hi>had pudled the ſtream; but after this you may finde S.</hi> Jerom <hi>&amp;c.</hi>]</p>
                  <p>That the Fathers of the firſt 400 years did ſpeak plainly and fully of it, is ſo evident as nothing
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:170258:50"/>more, and I appeal to their teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monies as they are ſet down in the papers annexed in their proper place; and therefore that muſt needs be one of the little arts by which ſome men uſe to eſcape from the preſſure of that authority, by which becauſe they would have other men concluded, ſometimes upon ſtrict inquiry they finde them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves entangled. Original Sin as it is at this day commonly expli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cated, was not the Doctrine of the primitive Church; but when <hi>Pelagius</hi> had pudled the ſtream, S. <hi>Auſtin</hi> was ſo angry that he ſtampt and diſturb'd it more: and truly my Lord, I do not think that the Gentlemen that urg'd againſt me S. <hi>Auſtin</hi>'s opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion, do well conſider that I pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſs my ſelf to follow thoſe fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers who were before him; and whom S. <hi>Auſtin</hi> did forſake as I
<pb n="97" facs="tcp:170258:50"/>do him in the queſtion. They may as well preſs me with his autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity in the Article of the damna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of Infants dying unbaptized, or of abſolute predeſtination. In which Article, S. <hi>Auſtin</hi>'s words are equally urged by the <hi>Janſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſts</hi> and <hi>Moliniſts,</hi> by the <hi>Remon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrants</hi> and <hi>Contra-remonſtrants,</hi> and they can ſerve both, and therefore cannot determine me. But then (My Lord) let it be remembred, that they are as much againſt S. <hi>Chryſoſtome</hi> as I am againſt S. <hi>Auſtin,</hi> with this only difference; that S. <hi>Chryſoſtome</hi> ſpeaks conſtantly in the argument, which S. <hi>Auſtin</hi> did not, and particularly in that part of it which concerns <hi>Concu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſcence.</hi> For in the inquiry, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther it be a ſin or no; he ſpeaks ſo variouſly, that though <hi>Calvin</hi> complains of him, that he cals
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:170258:51"/>it only an <hi>infirmity,</hi> yet he alſo brings teſtimonies from him to prove it to be a <hi>ſin,</hi> and let any man try if he can tie theſe words together. (<hi>De peccator. mer. et remiſsion. l.</hi> 1. <hi>c.</hi> 3.) <hi>Concupiſcen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tia carnis peccatum eſt, quia ineſt illi in obedientia contra dominatum mentis.</hi> Which are the words your Lordſhip quotes: Concupiſcence is a ſin becauſe it is a diſobedience to the Empire of the ſpirit. But yet in another place; (<hi>lib.</hi> 1. <hi>de civit. Dei cap.</hi> 25.) <hi>Illa Concupi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcentialis inobedientia quanto ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gis abſ<expan>
                           <am>
                              <g ref="char:abque"/>
                           </am>
                           <ex>que</ex>
                        </expan> culpa eſt in corpore non conſentientis, ſi abſ<expan>
                           <am>
                              <g ref="char:abque"/>
                           </am>
                           <ex>que</ex>
                        </expan> culpa eſt in corpore dormientis?</hi> It is a ſin and it is no ſin, it is criminal, but is without fault; it is culpable be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe it is a diſobedience, and yet this diſobedience without actual conſent is not culpable. If I do beleeve S. <hi>Auſtin,</hi> I muſt disbe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeve
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:170258:51"/>him; and which part ſoever I take, I ſhall be reproved by the ſame authority. But when the Fathers are divided from each other, or themſelves, it is indiffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent to follow either; but when any of them are divided from reaſon and Scripture, then it is not indifferent for us to follow <hi>them,</hi> and neglect <hi>theſe;</hi> and yet if theſe who object S. <hi>Auſtin</hi>'s autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity to my Doctrine, will be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent to ſubject to all that he ſaies, I am content they ſhall follow him in this too, provided that they will give me my liberty be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe I will not be tied to him that ſpeaks contrary things to himſelf, and contrary to them that went before him; and though he was a rare perſon, yet he was as fallible as any of my brethren at this day. He was followed by many ignorant ages, and all the world
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:170258:52"/>knowes by what accidental advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tages he acquired a great reputa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion: but he who made no ſcru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of deſerting all his predeceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſors, muſt give us leave upon the ſtrength of his own reaſons to quit his authority.</p>
                  <p>All that I ſhall obſerve is this, that the Doctrine of <hi>Original Sin</hi> as it is explicated by S. <hi>Auſtin,</hi> had two parents; one was the Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine of the <hi>Encratites,</hi> and ſome other Hereticks, who forbad Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riage, and ſuppoſing it to be evill, thought they were warranted to ſay, it was the bed of-ſin, and children the ſpawn of vipers and ſinners. And S. <hi>Auſtin</hi> himſelf, and eſpecially S. <hi>Hierom</hi> (whom your Lordſhip cites) ſpeaks ſome things of marriage, which if they were true, then marriage were highly to be refuſed, as being the increaſer of ſin rather then of
<pb n="101" facs="tcp:170258:52"/>children, and a ſemination in the fleſh, and contrary to the ſpirit, and ſuch a thing which being mingled with ſin, produces uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vocal iſſues, the mother and the daughter are ſo like that they are the worſe again. For if a proper inherent ſin be effected by chaſte marriages, then they are in this particular equal to adulterous em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braces, and rather to be <hi>pardoned</hi> then <hi>allowed;</hi> and if all <hi>Concupi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcence</hi> be vicious, then no marri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>age can be pure. Theſe things it may be have not been ſo much conſidered, but your Lordſhip I know remembers ſtrange ſayings in S. <hi>Hierom,</hi> in <hi>Athenagoras,</hi> and in S. <hi>Austin,</hi> which poſſibly have been countenanced and main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained at the charge of this opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion. But the other parent of this is the zeal againſt the <hi>Pelagian</hi> Hereſie, which did ſerve it ſelf
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:170258:53"/>by ſaying too little in this Arti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cle, and therefore was thought fit to be confuted by ſaying too much; and that I conjecture right in this affair, I appeal to the words which I cited out of S. <hi>Auſtin</hi> in the matter of Concupiſcence; concerning which he ſpeaks the ſame thing that I do, when he is diſingaged; as in his books <hi>De civitate Dei:</hi> but in his Tractate <hi>de peccatorum meritis &amp; remiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſione,</hi> which was written in his heat againſt the <hi>Pelagians</hi> he ſpeaks quite contrary. And who ever ſhall with obſervation read his one book of Original Sin againſt <hi>Pelagius,</hi> his two books <hi>de Nuptiis &amp; Concupiſcentia</hi> to <hi>Valerius,</hi> his three books to <hi>Marcellinus, de pec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>catorum meritis &amp; remiſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ione,</hi> his four books to <hi>Boniface, contra duas epiſtolas Pelagianorum,</hi> his ſix books to <hi>Claudius</hi> againſt <hi>Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lianus,</hi>
                     <pb n="103" facs="tcp:170258:53"/>and ſhall think himſelf bound to beleeve all that this ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent man wrote, will not only finde it impoſſible he ſhould, but will have reaſon to ſay, that zeal againſt an error is not alwaies the beſt inſtrument to finde out truth. The ſame complaint hath been made of others; and S. <hi>Jerome</hi> hath ſuffer'd deeply in the infir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mity. I ſhall not therefore trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble your Lordſhip with giving particular anſwers to the words of S. <hi>Jerom</hi> and S. <hi>Ambroſe,</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe (beſides what I have al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready ſaid) I do not think that their words are an argument fit to conclude againſt ſo much evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence, nor againſt a much leſs then that which I have every where brought in this Article, though indeed their words are capable of a fair interpretation, and beſides the words quoted out
<pb n="104" facs="tcp:170258:54"/>of S. <hi>Ambroſe</hi> are none of his; and for <hi>Aquinas, Lombard,</hi> and <hi>Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naventure,</hi> your Lordſhip might as well preſs me with the opinion of Mr. <hi>Calvin, Knox</hi> and <hi>Buchannan,</hi> with the Synod of <hi>Dort,</hi> or the <hi>Scots</hi> Presbyteries: I know they are againſt me, and therefore I re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prove them for it, but it is no diſparagement to the truth, that other men are in error. And yet of all the Schoolmen, <hi>Bonaven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture</hi> ſhould leaſt have been urg'd againſt me, for the proverbs ſake: for, <hi>Adam non peccavit in Bonaven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tura; Alexander</hi> of <hi>Hales</hi> would often ſay, that <hi>Adam</hi> never ſin'd in <hi>Bonaventure.</hi> But it may be he was not in earneſt: no more am I.</p>
                  <p>The laſt thing your Lordſhip gives to me in charge in the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>half of the objectors, is that <hi>I would take into conſideration the
<pb n="105" facs="tcp:170258:54"/>Covenant made between Almigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty God and</hi> Adam, <hi>as relating to his poſterity.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>To this I anſwer, that I know of no ſuch thing; God made a cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant with <hi>Adam</hi> indeed, and us'd the right of his dominion over his poſterity, and yet did no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing but what was juſt; but I finde in Scripture no mention made of any ſuch Covenant as is dreamt of about the matter of original ſin: only the Covenant of works God did make with all men till Chriſt came; but he did never exact it after <hi>Adam;</hi> but for a Covenant that God ſhould make with <hi>Adam,</hi> that if he ſtood, all his poſterity ſhould be I know not what; and if he fell, they ſhould be in a damnable conditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, of this (I ſay) there is <hi>nec vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>la nec veſtigium</hi> in holy Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture, that ever I could meet
<pb n="106" facs="tcp:170258:55"/>with: if there had been any ſuch covenant, it had been but equity that to all the perſons intereſſed it ſhould have been communicated, and caution given to all who were to ſuffer, and abilities given to them to prevent the evil: for elſe it is not a Covenant with them, but a decree concerning them; and it is impoſſible that there ſhould be a covenant made between two, when one of the par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties knowes nothing of it.</p>
                  <p>I will enter no further into this enquiry, but only obſerve, that though there was no ſuch co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant, yet the event that hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned might without any ſuch co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant have juſtly entred in at many doors. It is one thing to ſay that God by <hi>Adam</hi>'s ſin was moved to a ſeverer entercourſe with his poſterity, for that is cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly true; and it is another
<pb n="107" facs="tcp:170258:55"/>thing to ſay that <hi>Adam</hi>'s ſin of it ſelf did deſerve all the evill that came actually upon his chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren; Death is the wages of ſin, one death for one ſin; but not 10000 millions for one ſin; but therefore the Apoſtle affirms it to have deſcended on all, <hi>in as much as all men have ſin'd;</hi> But if from a ſinning Parent a good childe deſcends; the childs inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cence will more prevail with God for kindneſs, then the fathers ſin ſhall prevail for trouble. <hi>Non omnia parentum peccata dii in libe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ros convertunt, ſed ſiquis de ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lo naſcitur bonus, tanquam benè affectus, corpore natus de morboſo, is generis poena liberatur, tan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quam ex improbitatis domo, in ali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>am familiam datus: qui vero mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bo in ſimilitudinem generis refer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur at<expan>
                           <am>
                              <g ref="char:abque"/>
                           </am>
                           <ex>que</ex>
                        </expan> redigitur vitioſi, ei ni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mirum convenit tanquam haeredi
<pb n="108" facs="tcp:170258:56"/>debitas poenas vitii perſolvere,</hi> ſaid <hi>Plutarch (De iis qui ſero à Nu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine puniuntur. ex interpr. Clu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerii.)</hi> God does not alwaies make the fathers ſins deſcend upon the children. But if a good childe is born of a bad father, like a healthful body from an ill affected one, he is freed from the puniſhment of his ſtock, and paſſes from the houſe of wickedneſs in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to another family. But he who inherits the diſeaſe, he alſo muſt be heir of the puniſhment; <hi>Quo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum natura amplexa eſt cognatam malitiam, hos Juſtitia ſimilitudi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nem pravitatis perſequens ſuppli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cio affecit,</hi> if they purſue their kindreds wickedneſs, they ſhall be purſued by a cognation of judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</p>
                  <p>Other waies there are by which it may come to paſs that the ſins of others may deſcend upon us.
<pb n="109" facs="tcp:170258:56"/>He that is <hi>author</hi> or the <hi>perſwa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der,</hi> the <hi>miniſter</hi> or the <hi>helper,</hi> the <hi>approver</hi> or the <hi>follower,</hi> may de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rive the ſins of others to him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, but then it is not their ſins only, but our own too, and it is like a dead taper put to a burning light and held there, this derives light and flames from the other, and yet then hath it of its own, but they dwell together and make one body. Theſe are the waies by which puniſhment can enter, but there are evils which are no pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhments, and they may come upon more accounts, by <hi>Gods Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minion,</hi> by <hi>natural conſequence,</hi> by <hi>infection,</hi> by <hi>deſtitution</hi> and <hi>dere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liction,</hi> for <hi>the glory of God,</hi> by right of authority, for the <hi>inſtitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion</hi> or <hi>exerciſe</hi> of the ſuffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rers, or for their <hi>more immediate good.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <pb n="110" facs="tcp:170258:57"/>
                  <p>But that directly and properly one ſhould be puniſh'd for the ſins of others was indeed practi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed by ſome Common-wealths; <hi>Utilitatis ſpecie ſaepiſsimè in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pub. peccari,</hi> ſaid <hi>Cicero,</hi> they do it ſometimes for terror, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe their waies of preventing evil is very imperfect: and when <hi>Pedianus ſecundus</hi> the <hi>Pretor</hi> was kill'd by a ſlave, all the family of them was kill'd in puniſhment; this was <hi>ſecundum veterem morem</hi> ſaid <hi>Tacit.</hi> (<hi>Annal.</hi> 14.) for in the ſlaughter of <hi>Marcellus</hi> the ſlaves fled for fear of ſuch uſage; it was thus, I ſay, among the <hi>Romans,</hi> but <hi>habuit aliquid iniqui,</hi> and God forbid we ſhould ſay ſuch things of the fountain of Juſtice and mercy. But I have done, and will move no more ſtones, but hereafter carry them as long as I can, rather then make a noiſe by
<pb n="111" facs="tcp:170258:57"/>throwing them down; I ſhall only add this one thing: I was troubled with an objection lately; for it being propounded to me, why it is to be beleeved that the ſin of <hi>Adam</hi> could ſpoil the nature of man, and yet the nature of Devils could not be ſpoiled by their ſin which was worſe; I could not well tell what to ſay, and therefore I held my peace.</p>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <trailer>THE END.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="errata">
            <pb facs="tcp:170258:58"/>
            <head>An Advertiſement to the Reader.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>PAg.</hi> 8, &amp; 9 <hi>there are ſeven lines miſplaced, which are to be read thus: pag.</hi> 8. <hi>lin.</hi> 16. <hi>read,</hi> till the body was grown up to ſtrength enough to infect it] [and in the whole proceſs it muſt be an impoſſible thing, becauſe the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrument which hath all its operations by the force of the principal agent, cannot of it ſelf produce a great change and violent effect upon the principal agent] Beſides all this, (I ſay) while one does not know how Original Sin can be derived, and another who thinks he can, names a wrong way, and both the waies infer it to be another kinde of thing then all the Schools of learning teach: does it not too clearly demonſtrate,—</p>
         </div>
         <div type="publishers_advertisement">
            <pb facs="tcp:170258:58"/>
            <list>
               <head>The names of ſeveral Treatiſes and Sermons written by <hi>Jer. Taylor</hi> D.D.</head>
               <item>1. <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, a Courſe of Sermons for all the Sundaies in the year, together with a Diſcourſe of the Divine Inſtitution, Neceſſity and Separation of the Office Miniſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rial, in <hi>fol.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>2. Epiſcopacy aſſerted, in 4.</item>
               <item>3. The Hiſtory of the Life and Death of the Ever-bleſſed Jeſus Chriſt, 2. Edit. in <hi>fol.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>4. The Liberty of Propheſying, in 4.</item>
               <item>5. An Apologie for authoriſed and Set formes of Liturgie, in 4.</item>
               <item>6. The Rule and Exerciſes of holy li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving, in 12.</item>
               <item>7. The Rule and Exerciſes of holy dying, in 12.</item>
               <item>8. The Golden Grove, or, A Manual of daily Prayers fitted to the daies of the week, together with a ſhort Method of Peace and Holineſs.</item>
               <item>9. The Doctrine an practice of repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance reſcued from popular Er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rors, in a large 8. Newly publiſhed.</item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <pb facs="tcp:170258:59"/>
               <head>Books written by <hi>H. Ham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mond.</hi> D. D.</head>
               <item>A Paraphraſe and Annotations upon all the Books of the New Teſt. by <hi>H. Hammond</hi> D.D. in <hi>fol.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>2. <hi>The Practical Catechiſm,</hi> with all other Engliſh Treatiſes of <hi>H. Ham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mond,</hi> D. D. in two volumes in 4.</item>
               <item>3. <hi>Diſſertiones quatuor, quibus Epiſcopa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus Jura ex S. Scripturis &amp; primaeva Antiquitate adſtruuntur, contra ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentiam D.</hi> Blondelli <hi>&amp; aliorum. Authore</hi> Henrico Hammond, in 4.</item>
               <item>4. A Letter of Reſolution of ſix Que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries, in 12.</item>
               <item>5. Of Schiſm. A Defence of the Church of England, againſt the Exceptions of the Romaniſts, in 12.</item>
               <item>6. Of Fundamentals in a notion re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferring to practice, by <hi>H. Hammond</hi> D. D. in 12.</item>
               <item>7. Six books of late Controverſie in defence of the Church of England, in two volumes in 4. newly pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſhed.</item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <pb facs="tcp:170258:59"/>
               <head>Books newly publiſhed.</head>
               <item>DOctor <hi>Couſins</hi> Devotions, in 12. The perſecuted Miniſtery, by <hi>William Langley</hi> late of St. <hi>Maries</hi> in the City of <hi>Liechfield,</hi> Miniſter, in 4.</item>
               <item>A Diſcourſe of Auxiliary Beauty, or Artificial Handſomeneſſe. In point of Conſcience between two Ladies, in 8.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Lyford</hi>'s Legacy; or, an help to young People. Preparing them for the worthy receiving of the Lords Supper, in 12.</item>
               <item>The Principles of Holy Chriſtian Religion: or the Catechiſm of the Church of England paraphrazed. By <hi>R. Sherlock</hi> B. D. at <hi>Borwick Hall</hi> in <hi>Lancaſhire,</hi> in 8.</item>
               <item>A Diſcourſe. 1. Of the Holy Spirit of God, His Impreſſions and workings on the Souls of Men. 2. Of Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Revelation, Mediate and Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediate. 3. Of Error, Hereſie, and Schiſm: the Nature, Kindes, Cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, Reaſons, and Dangers thereof: with directions for avoiding the ſame. By <hi>R. Sherlock,</hi> B. D. in 4.</item>
            </list>
            <trailer>THE END.</trailer>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
